Guide to the Beaver Valley Labor History Society Collection, 1909-1981 AIS.1981.08
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Beaver Valley Labor History Society Collection
1909-1981
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Beaver Valley Labor History Society
AIS.1981.08
5 Linear Feet (5 boxes)
This collection contains material primarily documenting the successful 1930s organizing drive of the Steel Workers Organizing Committee of the Congress of Industrial Organizations at Jones and Laughlin Steel Corporation, Aliquippa, Pennsylvania. The organizing drive resulted in the landmark U.S. Supreme Court decision, National Labor Relations Board v. Jones and Laughlin Steel Corporation, which upheld the National Labor Relations Act and established the legal right to organize labor unions. The collection was created by members of the Beaver Valley Labor History Society who conducted oral history interviews, compiled subject files, and published a newsletter focused on the early history of what became United Steelworkers of America Local 1211. Recorded from 1978 to 1980, the collection's twenty-four oral histories also document the European immigrant experience in America; African American migration to the industrial north; work in a steel mill; and the social, political, economic, and cultural life of Aliquippa, 1900s-1930s.
History
With the support of United Steelworkers of America Local 1211 and the Philip Murray Retirees Club, the Beaver Valley Labor History Society was established in 1978 to "inform people of the important role that our valley has played in American labor history" so that "they may be aware and proud of their heritage." For a four year period, the Society collected material, conducted oral history interviews, and published a journal focused on documenting the history of steelworkers in Aliquippa, Pennsylvania. In 1981, the Beaver Valley Labor History Society transferred the organization's subject files, oral histories, and copies of its publications to the Archives of Industrial Society at the University of Pittsburgh and ceased publication of its journal.
Scope and Content Notes
This collection primarily covers the history of the 1930s Steel Workers Organizing Committee campaign at Jones and Laughlin Steel Corporation, Aliquippa, Pennsylvania, through original and photocopied materials. It also includes material on local and national issues related to the United Steelworkers Union from 1943-1981. Additionally, twenty-four oral history interviews, most of which are transcribed, with steelworkers and their family members who were involved in the 1930s Aliquippa organizing campaign provide additional insights. Further scope and content notes are provided at the series level.
Arrangement
Series I. Subject Files, 1909-1981
Series II. Oral Histories, 1978-1980
Series III. Publications
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Informaiton
Gift of Beaver Valley Labor History Society on October 1, 1981.
Previous Citation
Beaver Valley Labor History Society Collection, 1909-1981, AIS.1981.08, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Beaver Valley Labor History Society, 1934-1981 and Beaver Valley Labor History Society Collection, 1909-1981, UELAB.1981.08, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Existence and Location of Originals
The originals of some items in the collection are held by the Walter P. Reuther Library of Wayne State University and other repositories.
Related Material
Journal of the Beaver Valley Labor History Society, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
The Union Press (Aliquippa, Pa.), Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Separated Material
The microfilm reels can be found in cabinets in the Reading Room at the Archives Service Center.
Iron and steel workers -- Labor unions -- Organizing; Oral histories (Document genres); Iron and steel workers; Labor; Transcripts; Audiotapes; Ambridge (Pa.); Aliquippa (Pa.); Steel industry and trade -- Pennsylvania -- Aliquippa; Iron industry and trade -- Pennsylvania -- Aliquippa; United States. National Labor Relations Board -- Cases; Amalgamated Association of Iron, Steel, and Tin Workers of North America. Beaver Valley Lodge 200 (Aliquippa, Pa.); Bannik, Mike; Cobb, Clark; Colbert, Ella; Colonna, Nino; Steel Workers Organizing Committee (U.S.). Local 1211 (Aliquippa, Pa.); Cozzicoli, Mary; Del Turco, Dominic; Di Ciero, Joseph; Dunn, Ralph; Beaver Valley Labor History Society; George, Alex; Iacobucci, Bert; Jones & Laughlin Steel Corporation. Aliquippa Works; Kromerich, Frank; Lopata, Andy; Mandity, Joe; Modrack, Nick; Montini, Elizio; Montini, Ormond; Pienkowski, Frank; Riccitelli, Tony; Steel and Metal Workers Industrial Union (U.S.). Ambridge Office (Ambridge, Pa.); Tadora, Lou; Tipper, Bartow; Tomeo, Tony; United Steelworkers of America. Local 1211 (Aliquippa, Pa.); Uzelac, Eli; Zahorsky, Michael
- Subject Files, 1909-1981; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series primarily documents the Steel Workers Organizing Committee campaign at Jones and Laughlin Steel Corporation's Aliquippa Works during the 1930s. Also included is information on early labor relations in the Pennsylvania steel industry, the Steel and Metal Workers Industrial Union organizing drive in Ambridge from 1933-1935, and a selective history of the United Steelworkers Union spanning 1943-1981. The files are organized alphabetically by topic within each subseries and are almost entirely composed of photocopies of original documents held by other repositories.
  - Steel Industry Labor Relations, Pennsylvania, 1909-1932; 1.
    This subseries contains information on labor relations in the Pennsylvania steel industry prior to the union organizing drive of the 1930s. It contains photocopies of a variety of documents, including clippings.
    - American Federation of Labor, Smoky City Federal Local, Pittsburgh, Demands, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - American Iron and Steel Institute, Iron Age, Steel Company Towns including Aliquippa, 1909-1913 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Joe Dallet and the Jones and Laughlin Steel, Aliquippa Works Supervisor Bribery Scandal, May-June, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Jones and Laughlin Steel Corporation, "Pension System", July 24, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - United States Department of Labor, Deportation of United States Steel Employees, June 21, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - United States Department of Labor, Investigation of "Labor Trouble," Aliquippa, PA, October 9, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Woodlawn Gazette, Articles Regarding Steel Worker Union, Steel Industry and Ku Klux Klan, 1923-1924, 1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Steelworkers Organizing Drive, Aliquippa, 1933-1942; 2.
    This subseries documents the union organizing drive at Jones and Laughlin Steel Corporation's Aliquippa Works during the 1930s. It includes scattered documentation of local membership, finances, organization, and correspondence by union organizers and officers. Also included are proceedings, reports, and petitions related to U.S. National Steel Labor Relations Board hearings, 1934-1935, and U.S. National Labor Relations Board hearings, 1936. In addition, this subseries contains copies of clippings from labor and Pennsylvania newspapers related to this union campaign.
    - African Americans Expelled from Beaver County, PA, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Amalgamated Association of Iron, Steel and Tin Workers of North America, Aliquippa, 1933-1936, undated (Box 1, Folder 09-13)
    - Ambridge, PA, Steel Strike, September, 1933-May, 1935, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - American Federation of Labor, The AFL Rank and File Federationist, March-April, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - American Federation of Labor, List of Alleged Communist Party Members in SWOC, May 21, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - American Iron and Steel Institute, Employee Representation in the Iron and Steel Industry, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - American Iron and Steel Institute, Iron Age, Employee Representation Plans, June, 1934-March, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - American Iron and Steel Institute, Steel Facts, May 1935 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Bannik, Mike, December 1934-January 1935 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Beaver County Emergency Relief Board, Requests for Beaver Valley Lodge No. 200 Members, December, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Claessens, August and Rebecca E. Jarvis, ABC of Parliamentary Law, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Daily Worker, Steel Worker Union and Steel Industry, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Democratic Party, Beaver County, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Di Ciero, Joseph, Treasurer, SWOC Local 1211, Financial Scandal, July, 1938-December, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Federated Press, Steel Worker Union and Steel Industry, 1929-1934 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Foster, William Z., "Steel Workers - Organize!" from the Daily Worker, February 27, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Geographic and Demographic Material, Aliquippa, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Gerstner, Martin, Financial Secretary, Correspondence, August, 1934-May, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Hoenstine, Harry, "Address "Foremen's Club Meeting," Ellwood Works, National Tube Co., October 30, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Jones and Laughlin Steel Corporation, Company Spy Reports, February-May, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Jones and Laughlin Steel Corporation, Discharges, March, 1936-May, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Jones and Laughlin Steel Corporation, Employee Representation Plans, Aliquippa Works, 1934-1937 (Box 1, Folder 33-35)
    - Kane, M.J., Aliquippa Police Chief, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - League for Social Justice, "Report of the Ambridge Riot", 1933 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Marchione, L. and Frank, Correspondence in English and Italian, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Murray, Philip, "The Social and Economic Consequences of Technology", 1940 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Pennsylvania, Department of Labor and Industry, "Report....on Special Policing in Industry", October, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Philadelphia Record, Steel Worker Union and Steel Industry, 1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Pinchot, Glifford, "Statement ...", October 24, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Pucci, Guiseppi, Treasurer, Amalgamated Association of Iron, Steel and Tin Workers, Finances, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Ruttenberg, Harold J., Correspondence, July, 1934 - July, 1935, November 19, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Song Sheets, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Steel and Metal Workers Industrial Union, Aliquippa Local, Hot Billet, March 1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Steel and Metal Workers Industrial Union, Steel Metal Worker, August, 1933 - June, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 47-51)
    - Steel and Metal Workers Industrial Union, Steel Workers Organize and Prepare to Strike, 1930s (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Steel Workers Organizing Committee, Handling Grievances, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Steel Workers Organizing Committee, "Jones and Laughlin Steel Corporation Basic Contract", May 25, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Steel Workers Organizing Committee Lodge No. 1211, Organizing Drive, June, 1936-July, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Steel Workers Organizing Committee and Jones and Laughlin Steel Corp., Agreement, May 14, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Timko, Joseph J., "Report ...Steel Workers Organizing Committee, Beaver Valley District", January 17, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - United States Bureau of Mediation, "Complaint, Beaver Valley Lodge No. 200", March 9, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - United States Labor Relations Board, "Official Report ...Jones and Laughlin Steel Corp.", 1936 (Box 1, Folder 59-76)
    - United States National Steel Labor Relations Board, August, 1934-October, 1935, undated (Box 2, Folder 01-02)
    - United States National Steel Labor Relations Board, "Findings... Jones and Laughlin Steel Corp.", 1935 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - United States National Steel Labor Relations Board, "Petition for Re-Hearing...Lodge No. 200", 1935 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - United States National Steel Labor Relations Board, "Report ...Jones and Laughlin Steel Corp.", 1934 (Box 2, Folder 05-07)
    - United States National War Labor Board, "Notice to Employees of Jones and Laughlin Steel Corp.", 1942 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - United Steelworkers of America, Steel Labor, August, 1936-March, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 09-10)
    - Western Pennsylvania Unemployment Council, Hunger Fighter, Special Steel Strike Edition, June 19, 1934 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Young Worker, Steel Worker Union and Steel Industry, 1930s (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - United Steelworkers of America, Local 1211, 1943-1981; 3.
    This subseries documents a broad range of local and national issues related to steel industry labor relations and the internal union politics of the United Steelworkers. Also included is some material related to the International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers Local 201, Beaver, PA, from the 1970s. The bulk of this material consists of printed documents or clippings.
    - Affirmative Action and Civil Rights, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Aliquippa Democratic Social Club, 1950, 1953, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Beaver Valley Gazette, Steel Worker Union and Steel Industry, November 1950 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Historical Development, Aliquippa, ca.1970 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers Local 201, Beaver, PA, 1973-1979 (Box 2, Folder 17-22)
    - Johnson, J. Bruce, United States Steel Corporation, Ambridge Bridge Division, October, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - National Steelworkers Rank and File Committee, "Convention Report", August, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - North American Congress on Latin America Report on the Americas, "Steelyard Blues", 1979 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Steel Worker Union and Steel Industry Articles, 1910s-1940s, December, 1978-April, 1980, undated (Box 2, Folder 26-29)
    - Story of the Woodlawn Land Company, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - United States Labor Party, August, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - United Steelworkers of America, "Agreement ... Jones and Laughlin Steel Corp.", 1962 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - United Steelworkers of America, "Constitution of International Union, Manual ...", September 18, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - United Steelworkers of America, Contract Negotiation, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - United Steelworkers of America, Experimental Negotiating Agreement, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - United Steelworkers of America, National Convention, August, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - United Steelworkers of America, Proposed Constitutional Amendments, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - United Steelworkers of America, Steel Labor, "Fortieth Anniversary Issue", May-June, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - United Steelworkers of America Local 1211, Aliquippa Steelworker, 1964 -1966, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - United Steelworkers of America Local 1211 Elections, January, 1940-December, 1943 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - United Steelworkers of America and the Coordinating Committee Steel Companies, "Contracting Out", 1979 (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Oral Histories, 1978-1980; II.
  This series is comprised of twenty-three oral history interviews of steelworkers involved in the Steel Workers Organizing Committee union recognition drive in Aliquippa during the 1930s. In addition to the early history of unionism in the area, the interviews cover a broad range of topics including immigration from Europe; work in a steel mill; and the social, political, economic and cultural life of Aliquippa. The interviews were conducted by members of the Beaver Valley Labor History Society from 1978-1980. Seventeen of the interviews have been fully or partially transcribed.
  - Cobb, Clark (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Colonna, Nino (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Cozzicoli, Mary (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Del Turco, Dominic (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Di Ciero, Joe (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Dunn, Ralph (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - George, Alex (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Iacobucci, Bert (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Kromerich, Frank (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Lopata, Andy (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Mandity, Joe (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Modrack, Nick (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Montini, Elizio (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Montini, Ormond (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Riccitelli, Tony (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Tadora, Lou (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Zahorsky, Michael (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Humeniuk, Paul (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Bannik, Mike (Box 3, Cassette 1)
  - Cobb, Clark (Box 3, Cassette 2)
  - Colbert, Ella (Box 3, Cassette 3)
  - Colonna, Nino (Box 3, Cassette 4)
  - Cozzicoli, Mary (Box 3, Cassette 5)
  - Del Turco, Dominic (Box 3, Cassette 6)
  - Di Ciero, Joe (Box 3, Cassette 7)
  - Dunn, Ralph (Box 3, Cassette 8)
  - Iacobucci, Bert (Box 3, Cassette 9)
  - Kromerich, Frank (Box 3, Cassette 10)
  - Lopata, Andy (Box 3, Cassette 11)
  - Mandity, Joe (Box 3, Cassette 12)
  - Modrack, Nick (Box 3, Cassette 13)
  - Montini, Elizio (Box 3, Cassette 14)
  - Montini, Ormond (Box 3, Cassette 15)
  - Pienkowski, Frank (Box 3, Cassette 16)
  - Riccitelli, Tony (Box 3, Cassette 17)
  - Tadora, Lou (Box 3, Cassette 18)
  - Tipper, Bartow (Box 3, Cassette 19)
  - Tomeo, Tony (Box 3, Cassette 20)
  - Uzelac, Eli (Box 3, Cassette 21)
  - Zahorsky, Michael (Box 3, Cassette 22)
  - unidentified (Box 3, Cassette 23)
  - Humeniuk, Paul (Box 3, Cassette 24)
- Publications, III.
  This series contains microfilmed copies of Beaver Valley Labor History Journal, which was produced by the Beaver Valley Labor History Society, and The Union Press, which was produced by SWOC 1211 in Aliquippa, Pa. In addition to the microfilmed newspapers of The Union Press, the originals have been retained.
  - Beaver Valley Labor History Journal Volume 1-Volume 3, 1979-1981 (Microfilm-cabinet 3, Drawer 9, Reel 1)
  - The Union Press, Aliquippa, Pa., August 11-October 29, 1937 (Microfilm-cabinet 4, Drawer 3, Reel 2)
  - The Union Press, Aliquippa, Pa., Volume 1-Volume 3, August 11-October 29, 1937 (Microfilm-cabinet 4, Drawer 3, Reel 1)
  - The Union Press, August 25-October 29, 1937 (Map-case 3, Drawer 11)
- Additions, 2009-2016; IV.
  This series includes files pertaining to Service Employees International Union Local 585 and newsletters from their Beaver County Public Employee Coalition. Also present are issues of the Union Bug, the newsletter of the AFL-CIO Labor Council of Beaver County, dating from 1984 to 1994. The Social Democratic Club Banner represents Social Democratic Club where amalgamated unions met to organize into the CIO.
  The highlight of this series is a photograph of Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. and Raymond "Moose" Marsilio, President of Transportation Workers Union Local 2035 in Conway, Pennsylvania. The photo was taken at the 1961 TWU convention in New York City, where Dr. King was the keynote speaker. Dr. King autographed the photo: "Good Luck Moose M Luther King Jr."
  - Labor Council of Beaver County Newsletter, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Union Bug, Labor Council of Beaver County, 1984-1987 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Union Bug, Labor Council of Beaver County, 1988-1990 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Union Bug, Labor Council of Beaver County, 1991-1994 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - SEIU Local 585, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Beaver County Public Employee Coalition Bulletin, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Grass Roots" Report: A Political Action Newsletter, Butler County United Labor Council, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Labor Rallies and Events, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Fact Sheets (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Petitions (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Elections, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Photograph: Dr. Martin Luther King, Jr. and Raymond "Moose" Marsilio, TWU Convention, New York City, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Social Democratic Club Banner (Box 5, Item 1)